Course Project: Traffic Rule Violation Detection
AID 728
1 Overview
In this project, you will design a computer vision system to detect traffic rule violations involving
two-wheelers from street images. The goal is to build a robust, efficient, and modular system
under strict resource constraints.
2 Problem Statement
Given a single RGB image captured from a street scene, your system must:
1. Detect all two-wheelers (motorcycles/scooters).
2. Identify whether any of the following violations occur:
•More than two riders on a two-wheeler.
•One or more riders not wearing a helmet.
•Not wearing a helmet and more than two riders.
3. For each violating vehicle, extract and report theregistration number (license plate).
3 Constraints
•Model Size Limit:Total size of all model files must not exceed250 MB.
•No Large Models:Use of large Vision-Language Models (e.g.,>1B parameters) is
prohibited.
•Offline Execution:Internet access will be disabled during evaluation.
•Inference Efficiency:The system should process each image within a reasonable time.
4 Output Format
For each input image, your system must return a JSON-compatible dictionary:
{
"violations": [
{
"num_riders": int,
"helmet_violations": int,
"license_plate": "string"
}
]
}
where:
1
•num riders: Total number of riders detected.
•helmet violations: Number of riders not wearing helmets.
•license plate: Recognized license plate string.
5 Submission Structure
Each submission must follow the exact directory format:
<ROLL_NUMBER>/
solution.py
models/ (required, <= 250 MB total)
requirements.txt (required)
README.md (required)
6 Mandatory Class Interface
Students must implement the following class insolution.py:
class TrafficViolationDetector:
def __init__(self, model_dir="./models": str):
"""
Initialize and load all models here.
model_dir: path to directory containing model weights.
"""
pass
def predict(self, image_path: str) -> dict:
"""
Input:
image_path: Path to input image
Output:
{
"violations": [
{
"num_riders": int,
"helmet_violations": int,
"license_plate": "string"
}
]
}
"""
pass
7 Execution Protocol
During evaluation:
1. The evaluator will dynamically import your class.
2. The model will be initialized once:
model = TrafficViolationDetector(model_dir) #model_dir should be ./models
2
3. For each image:
output = model.predict(image_path)
8 Evaluation Protocol
Evaluation will be fully automated using ground-truth annotations.
8.1 Metrics
•Violation Classification Accuracy:
–Correct rider count.
–Correct helmet violation detection.
•License Plate Recognition Accuracy:
–Exact string match or normalized edit distance.
8.2 Final Score
Score =w 1 ·Violation +w 2 ·OCR (1)
9 Implementation Guidelines
•You may use pretrained models (e.g., YOLO, OCR systems).
•Depth estimation models (e.g., Depth Anything) may be used if helpful.
•You are encouraged to design a modular pipeline.
•The system must be robust to:
–Occlusions
–Low lighting
–Small or blurry license plates
10 Important Rules
•All models must be loaded inside the class constructor.
•predict()must be stateless (no dependency on previous calls).
•Output format must be strictly followed.
•Any runtime errors will result in zero score for that sample.
•Submissions violating model size constraints will be disqualified.
11 Deliverables
•Complete source code
•Model weights (within size limit)
•Report (recommended, to perform analysis as well as show the failure cases)
3
12 Grading Notes
•This is primarily anengineering-focused project.
•Emphasis will be on:
–Robustness
–System design
–Failure handling
•Solutions that generalize well will score higher.
4

